<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">&lt;ܬܸ݂&gt; – Towards Bidirectional TEI</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename><!-- this author's forename --></forename> 
                  <surname><!-- this author's surname --></surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation><!-- a prose description of this author's affiliation, containing <roleName> and <orgName>--></affiliation>
               <email><!-- this author's email address --></email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date><!-- the publication year --></date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence> 
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <!-- a list of keywords, each in its own <term> -->
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change><!-- Description of a change to the article; we recommend using @who and @when. --></change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract"
            ><p>Encoding right-to-left script in TEI-XML is a hassle unless one uses an editor that hides away
               the tags. The problem arises from element names in Latin script interrupting the
               right-to-left rendering of content on the editor screen, which is handled by the
               Unicode Bidirectional Algorithm. However, hiding the tags is not the only solution.
               With <gi>altIdent</gi>, TEI offers a means for declaring alternative names for
               elements and attributes: names in another language and even in another script. Thus,
               we can have valid right-to-left-only TEI documents in XML version 1.1, which are
               readable and editable while tags are visible.</p>
            <p>However, using <gi>altIdent</gi> quickly feels like introducing entropy to the
               schema. Therefore, the paper suggests not to translate names, but to
                  <hi>transliterate</hi> them. Compared to translation, transliteration is a
               mechanical process which can be done by a machine without much coding effort. An
               implementation is at hand in the Unicode ICU library,<note/> and there is even an
               XPath binding for this library,<note/> so that transliteration is available in XSLT
               and XQuery. Thus, generating a full ODD with Arabic, Syriac, or Hebrew, etc. element
               and attribute aliases becomes quite simple and fast. The &amp;lt;ܬܸ݂&amp;gt; from the
               title of this paper is a <gi>TEI</gi> tag transliterated to Syriac script.</p>
            <p>Transforming a TEI document with alterative names to its equivalent with Latin script
               names is always possible en route the mapping of identifiers and alternative
               identifiers deposited in the ODD. Direct re-transliteration of alternative names is
               only possible under certain preconditions. For example, transliterating <q>TEI</q> to
               Arabic script and back to Latin script gives <gi>tii</gi>, since the transliterator
               maps the inventory of latin vovels to a non-compatible inventory; furthermore Arabic
               is a unicameral script, so that case information is lost. Syriac script is very good
               suited for transliterating from Latin script and back to; and albeit it is a
               unicameral script we can add escape sequences to the transliteration, so that a fully
               invertable transliteration can be achieved without consulting the ODD.</p>
            <p>The paper will first analyse the problem when bidirectional text is displayed on a
               screen, and it will show how wellformed tags look like in RTL script. It will then
               introduce transliteration of XML names in documents and ODDs. It will discuss
               challenges regarding attributes in the XML namespace, especially
               <att>xml:id</att>.</p></div>
      </front>
      <body>
      <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->
         <div xml:id="firstdiv">
            <head/>
            <p>
               <ref type="bibl" target="#bloggs13">Bloggs 2013</ref> tells us...</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="seconddiv">
            <head/>
            <p/>
         </div>
      </body>
    
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
        <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bloggs13"/>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
